<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prælium &amp; præmium. The Christians warre and rewarde A sermon preached before the Kings maiestie at VVhitehall the 3. of May. 1608. By Daniell Price Master of Arts of Exeter Colledge, and chapleyn in ordinarie to the prince</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113692</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848923</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848923</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14045</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1460:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prælium &amp; præmium. The Christians warre and rewarde A sermon preached before the Kings maiestie at VVhitehall the 3. of May. 1608. By Daniell Price Master of Arts of Exeter Colledge, and chapleyn in ordinarie to the prince</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication to the Archbishop of Canterbury.</note>
                  <note>On Rev. ii.26.</note>
                  <note>"The dedication implies that the book took four days to print (?), and claims to be the first from the University Press since the archbishop (Richard Bancroft) became Chancellor (23 Apr. 1608)."--Madan, Oxford Books I, p. 71 ʻ.</note>
                  <note>Page 15 misnumbered 5; 25-28 missing; text is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14045:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14045:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Praelium &amp; praemium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS WARRE and rewarde.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED before the Kings Maieſtie at VVhite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall <hi>the</hi> 3. <hi>of May.</hi> 1608.</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>DANIELL PRICE <hi>Maſter of Arts of Exeter Colledge, and Chapleyn in ordinarie to the</hi> PRINCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincenti dabitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14045:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14045:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, THE LORD</hi> Arch-biſhop of Canterburie his Grace, Primat and Metrapolitan of all England, one of his Maieſties moſt Honorable priuie Counſel, &amp; the right worthy Chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celour of the famous Vniuerſitie of Oxford.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost reverend, religious, &amp; right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honourable, ſo ſmall a preſent for ſo great a <hi>Patrone</hi> is not tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by the rule of proportion, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie when ſo great weakneſse lyeth open to the eie of ſo great worthineſſe. My apprehenſion at the firſt conceited mee ſo ſtrongly that I deſigned this to aternal oblivion &amp; reſolved that it ſhoulde haue dyed and beene buried in the place it first breathed, but fearing leſt an action of preſumption would bee commenced againſt mee, for burying ſo poore an <hi>Orphan</hi> in ſo princely a place as <hi>the Kings Chappel,</hi> I adventured to lay it in the graue of the preſse, wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it in theſe <hi>ſheetes,</hi> as in a <hi>Syndon,</hi> &amp; mantling it on a <hi>ſable</hi> letter, as in a <hi>hearſe,</hi> and yet after foure aates preſsing to death, it revived, and is crept to preſent it ſelfe vnto your Grace preſuming that as you affoorded it gratious <hi>attention</hi> at the <hi>preaching,</hi> ſo you will affoord it gratious <hi>acception</hi> in the <hi>printing.</hi> If there bee anie thing worthy Patronadge in it, or in mee, I humbly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it, reioycing much I may tender any obſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, whom his roiall Maieſtie, the gracious Queene,
<pb facs="tcp:14045:3"/>my Princely Maſter, the nobleſt Perſonadges, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test ſchollers, both the Vniverſities, the Church, Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, arts and ſchooles, doe for his studies, conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, labours, &amp; imployme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, acknowledge, reverence, and preferre to the Confluence of all honour. I muſt confeſſe it had manie verie honorable friends who deſired after the preaching to bee acquainted with it, but I was then doubtful whether I ſhould publiſh it or no, ſomtimes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving it, ſometimes reſolving for it, til now at length I haue adventured to let it ſee the ſunne. It is the first tender of my dutie, and the first dedication fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity Preſſe,</hi> ſince the time your Grace was pleaſed to entertaine the protection of vs. The Lord preſerue your Grace to continue for manie and manie yeeres, that the Church may long enioie ſo worthie a <hi>Piller,</hi> the Common wealth ſo wiſe a <hi>Counſeller,</hi> and this famous Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ſo honourable a <hi>Chauncellour.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Exeter Coll.</hi> 
                  <date>this 19. of June. 1608.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Graces, in all humble dutie DANIELL PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14045:3"/>
            <head>The Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. 2.26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He that overcommeth, &amp; keepeth my works to the ende, to him will I giue power over nations.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE whole booke of God writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his finger, deliuered by his power, inſpired by his ſpirit, and revealed by his will, is as <hi>Caſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> obſerueth, <hi>Schola coeleſt is, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruditio vitalis, auditorium veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, diſciplina ſingularis,</hi> profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to teach, to inſtruct, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, to correct, that the man of God may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in al good works: whatſoeuer is contained in this booke, God hath reuealed to man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is become <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſecretum, relatum,</hi> nay not only <hi>relatum</hi> but <hi>revelatum,</hi> The whole booke from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> is the <hi>Geneſis</hi> of a <hi>Revelation,</hi> here beginneth the <hi>Exodus</hi> the end, termination, complement, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the Reuelation. <hi>Iob</hi> may conceaue <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Dei,</hi> Iob. 11.6. <hi>Daniel</hi> may obſerue <hi>abſcondita Dei. Dan.</hi> 2.22. The Apoſtle may diſcerne <hi>profunda Dei,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. And <hi>Paule</hi> wrapped vp to the thirde hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens may heare <hi>arcana Dei,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. But now <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creta, profunda, arcana, abſcondita,</hi> be <hi>revelata.</hi> The Aenigma is diſcloſed, the knot vnlooſed, the myſteries interpreted, the vaile remoued, all things reuealed, &amp; he that was vailed in the fleſh is reuealed in the ſpirit, and in this booke, is the manifeſtation of our <hi>God</hi> &amp; of his <hi>will,</hi> of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and of his <hi>life,</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14045:4"/>of his <hi>truth,</hi> of his <hi>ſeales, trumpets, angels, viols, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, lightnings, threatnings, iudgements</hi> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hel, the earth, the ſea, conſumption, deſtruction, diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſolation and final conſumation of the world.</p>
            <p>Jf the whole Scripture may bee called the <hi>Librarie</hi> of the holy Ghoſt, then this is the <hi>Cloſet</hi> of that <hi>libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> if the <hi>Lanthorne</hi> of Jſrael, then this is the <hi>light</hi> of that <hi>Lanthorne,</hi> if the Alphabet of God, then this is then of that Alphabet, this is the <hi>ende</hi> of his booke, who is the <hi>beginning</hi> and the <hi>end,</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> of his book, who is the <hi>firſt</hi> and the <hi>laſt,</hi> the Ω of his booke, who is α and Ω, the <hi>Amen</hi> of his booke, who is <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi> The <hi>holyeſt</hi> place not more worthily called <hi>ſanctum ſanctorum,</hi> or the <hi>Iubile Sabbatum ſabbatorum,</hi> or the <hi>Canticles Cantica Canticorum,</hi> or <hi>Empireum Coelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum,</hi> I ſay not more truely called ſo, then this <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Revelationum,</hi> the <hi>Compendium</hi> and <hi>Epitome</hi> of all the works, wonders, ſecrets, depths, and miſteries of God, ſo that as a father well ſpeaketh of the whole ſcripture,<note place="margin">Hugo.</note> I may alſo in particular ſpeake of this <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calips, paſcit miraculis, oraculis, figuris, verbis, myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Morall</note> And as <hi>Manna</hi> as <hi>Gregory</hi> obſerueth, <hi>habet omne delectamentum, &amp; omnis ſaporis ſuauitatem,</hi> ſo I may ſpeake of this booke of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> (which is the hid <hi>Manna,</hi> kept long in the <hi>Arke, inter arcana,</hi> and now manifeſted among <hi>Reuelata.</hi>) O then come, and ſee, and ſee heare, and taſte how good and ſweete this <hi>Manna</hi> is, it wil giue to euerie man his guſt &amp; relliſh, if yee be ignorant here yee may be inſtructed, if weak, heare yee may be ſtrengthned, if feareful, here ye may be hartened, if fighting here yee may be comforted, if
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14045:4"/>triumphing, here yee maie be crowned, and more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, here is the greateſt bleſſing pronounced that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was to anie booke, Bleſſed is he that readeth,<note place="margin">Revel 1.</note> &amp; he that heareth, and he that vnderſtandeth, and hee that keepeth the words of this booke.</p>
            <p>Out of this book &amp; out of that Manna of this booke haue J choſen this portion of ſcripture, as a portion of meate in due ſeaſon, which if you wil ſtaye till J haue prepared it for you, J will preſent it to bee <hi>panem noſtrum hodiernum,</hi> or rather, <hi>panem nostrum quotidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum. He that overcometh and keepeth my workes to the end to him wil I giue power ouer nations.</hi> what ſubiect more ſit for Heroicall ſpirits then an encitement to chiualtrie, nay what ſubiect maie ſpeake of a fitter ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect before a moſt royal King, then of a kingdome. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde both theſe in this <hi>Hee that ouercometh &amp;c.</hi> Hee that ouercometh, here a chriſtian is made a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>and keepeth my woorks to the end,</hi> hereof a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour</hi> he is made a <hi>Continuer,</hi> J wil giue him power ouer nations, hereof a <hi>Continuer</hi> he is made a king. <hi>He that ouercometh</hi> here hee is approued a <hi>Chriſtian and keepeth my woorkes,</hi> here hee is a <hi>Catholike, I will giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him power over nations,</hi> here he is <hi>Defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of the faith</hi> A Conquerour, a Continuer, a King, a Chriſtian, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, Defender of the faith. In a woorde in theſe woords ye ſhal finde, a Conflict, &amp; a Conqueſt, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres miſerie, Saints dignitie, the ſtate of ſeruants, in this life laborious, the ſtate of Saints in the life to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e glorious, a precept to take vp the Croſſe, a promiſe of the Crowne, an exhortation from God to man, a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penſation for man from God. All this in theſe wordes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14045:5"/>
               <hi>hee that ouercometh and keepeth my woorkes to the ende I will giue him power ouer nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerue breefly theſe 2 parts <hi>praelium &amp; pramium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diuiſ.</note> 
               <hi>praelium admortem; praemium advitam,</hi> a warre, and a rewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, warre to the end, the end of that end to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, <hi>In praelio,</hi> in the warrfare obſerue, 1 that the true Chriſtian muſt ouercome,<note place="margin">Subdiuiſ.</note> 
               <hi>He that ouercometh,</hi> 2. that he muſt continue, <hi>and keepe my workes to the end, in praemio,</hi> the reward, obſerue 1. the giuer promiſing. <hi>I will giue him.</hi> 2. the gift promiſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>power ouer nations</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hus you ſee the body and ſoule, the heauen &amp; earth of my Text, the parts and particular circumſtance, thereof, of al which in their order, and firſt of the firſt. <hi>He that ouercometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man the Modell of the worlde in reſpect of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, <note place="margin">1. Obſ.</note> hath his life co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to things moſt mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary. by <hi>Eſchilus</hi> to ſmoak, by <hi>Varro</hi> to a bubble, by <hi>Crates</hi> to hey, by <hi>Socrates</hi> to a <hi>Iourney,</hi> by <hi>Epictetus</hi> to a <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> by <hi>Pindarus</hi> to a <hi>ſhadowe,</hi> by <hi>Plutarch</hi> to a <hi>Flower</hi> by <hi>Petrarch</hi> to a <hi>feather,</hi> by <hi>Iacob</hi> to a <hi>Pilgrimage. Gen.</hi> 47.9. wherin is caſualtie by <hi>Dauid</hi> to a ſpan. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 39.5. wherein is breuitie by <hi>Hoſea,</hi> to a cloud, <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 13.3. wherein is mutabilitie, by <hi>Paul</hi> to a Race. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. wherin is Celeritie, by <hi>Iames</hi> to a vapour. <hi>Iames</hi> 4.13. wherin is inconſtancie, &amp; by <hi>Iob</hi> to a warfare. <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.7. wherin is much conflicting miſerie, God that is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, a man of warre, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.3. made man alſo to bee a man of warre. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. put emnitie betweene the woman and the ſerpent, &amp; betweene the feed of the woman and the feed of the ſerpent. In the 3. of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis you maie ſee the begining of this warre, there was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14045:5"/>the firſt quarrell about the firſt broken head, <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>hee ſhall breake thine head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</hi> here vpon the challenge was proclaymed, the Campe pitched, the battell fought, and the hatred continued euen to this houre. Herevpon God prouided for man an armour, knighted him a Chriſtian, prepared the Croſſ for his enſigne, blood for his Colours, Chriſt for his Captaine, and taught his hands to fight, &amp; his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to battel, ſo that now <hi>Iob</hi> maie trulie ſpeake <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia eſt vita hominis ſuper terram, non ſuper coelum qui ſuper coelum triumphant, non ſub terra qui ſub terra quie ſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſed ſuper terram quia qui ſuper terram pugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Tſaba</hi> as the Hebrews read a continuall dimication, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the Greekes a Piracie by ſea &amp; a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie by land or a <hi>temptation,</hi> as the ſeptuagint tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it, a Conflict, Combat, battel, a warring agoniz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kinde of life, in which al <hi>quoad maius &amp; minus</hi> haue their partes as <hi>Petrarch</hi> obſerueth, <hi>Hic in caſtris, ille in Roſtris, in ſcholis, in memore an agro, in pelago, in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat ſo: hic ferro corpus, ille animum dolis, hic argutijs lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam armat, hic pedibus, ille equo, hic currit, ille nauigat omnes militant.</hi> Many ſtriue ſaith the Apoſtle but one receaueth the Crowne, ſo many ſight but there is but one ſort of ſouldiers that receaue the reward. <hi>Benaiah</hi> was honorable among thirtie but he attained not to the firſt 3, And ſo many a <hi>Benatah</hi> may fight and yet in fighting not attaine to the holie warfare of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is the firſt three. Therefore as there is a Soe runne that ye maie obtaine, ſo alſo is there ſoe fight that yee maie ouercome, <hi>Non pugnanti, ſed vincenti,</hi> Not to him that fighteth, but to him that ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14045:6"/>the aime, the marke, the ſcope, the end, the <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſura</hi> the <hi>Cauſa Cauſae</hi> of our fighting to ouercome. To him that ouercommeth. But is man able to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, hath he power to wil, wil to deſire, deſire to ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect, effect to continue. Hath he ſtrength to ſtand that is ſo weake, force to fight, that is ſo wearie, meanes to ouercome, that is ſo vnworthie. The <hi>Pelagian</hi> and his heire apparant of that hereſie <hi>Bellarmine in his</hi> 5. <hi>book de gratia &amp; libero arbitrio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lib. 5. de gra. &amp; lib. arb.</note> anſwere that man though he be ſeeble, weake, wearie, vnworthie, yet hath he li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berty, and ſtrength, and free wil to run, &amp; to continue and perſeuere, elſe were al precepts and exhortations and expoſitions and reproofes altogither in vaine. For as the <hi>Pedeſtri ſenatores</hi> among the Papiſts aske what follie were it to exhort, or commande vs, to doe that which is not within our power, or liberty to performe, it were as if a man ſhould exhort one to runne, which were faſt incloſed in a priſon. For anſwere whereunto I ſaie <hi>Auſtine</hi> by anticipation in his booke <hi>de gratia &amp; libero arbitrio,</hi> anſwereth <hi>Bell.</hi> argument in his booke <hi>de gratia &amp; libero arbitrio. Ideo Deus, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore God commaundeth ſomewhat that man cannot doe, that man maie learne to ſeeke abilitie of God to doe it, <hi>Fides enim impetrat quod lex imperat,</hi> for faith ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines from God by praier, what God preſcribeth to man by law. So that the Imperatiue in God begets an Optatiue in man, not an Operatiue: and therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>David</hi> in one verſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> we read <hi>Tu praecepisti,</hi> thou haſt charged that we ſhould keepe thy commandements, hee addeth <hi>vtinam ſic vie meae parentur,</hi> O that my waies were made ſo direct, that I might keepe thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14045:6"/>his commande <hi>excitants gratia,</hi> his aſſiſtance <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perans gratiam.</hi> Commandement maie extende fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſtrength, but Gods aſſiſtance ſtretcheth as far as his commandement. He hath not only in an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded <hi>Reuertere</hi> Returne, but alſo in a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue <hi>Convertere,</hi> be thou conuerted, and therefore mans power is neuer operant vnleſſe God be Coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. We are al as ſpring lockes, ſhut wee can of our ſelues, not open, for our <hi>naturales Potentiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin.</note> as the ſchooles ſpeake, be become <hi>naturales impotentiae,</hi> and as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Libero arbitrio male vtens ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo &amp; ſe perdidit &amp; ip ſum.</hi> So that whoſoeuer will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder muſt acknowledge ſtill <hi>Dominus ſuper ſcala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and howſoeuer the ſword of the Lord and the ſword of Gedeon maie goe togither, yet the hand of Gedeon or the ſword in his hand, or the edge on his ſworde is not able to pierce vnleſſe God giue power, <hi>Non enim tam agimus quam à Deo agimur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch.</note> ſaieth <hi>Zanchius,</hi> for man is not ſo properlie ſaid to doe good, as to be compelled to doe it by the good ſpirit of God. And the Apoſtle teacheth, that it is not in him that willeth or in him that runneth, but in God which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableth vs, we can doe al things. <hi>Auſten</hi> endeth al this in his 3. booke <hi>de lib. Arbit.</hi> 16. <hi>Eſay. Deus &amp; velle praecepit &amp; poſse praebuit et non impune nolle permiſit.</hi> God commands all men to be willing, he giueth vnto ſome his grace to be able, he permitteth others to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vnwilling but neuer to remaine vnpuniſhed. And therfore our prayer muſt be as the ſame fathers is, <hi>Da Domine quod iubes &amp; iube quod vis,</hi> giue vs O Lord abilitie to doe what thou commandeſt, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14045:7"/>what thou wilt, for without thee our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is ignorance, our power is infirmitie, our ſight is blindnes, our light is darknes, our ſtrength is weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But J have founded a retrait too longe from my warfare, <hi>he that ouer commeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The heathens had ſundrie times, at which they did eſpecially practiſe militarie actions, and points of chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualtie, &amp; had their <hi>Nemea, Istmia, Pythia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Olympia,</hi> in which they did exerciſe ſtriuing, wreſtling, runing, fighting, and other feats of Martialiſme. The verie ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e exerciſes hath God appointed for his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, he hath appointed them to runne, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. <hi>per viam man datorum.</hi> Pſ. 119.32. <hi>per viam patientiae. Heb.</hi> 12.1. he hath appointed them to reſiſt. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.13. <hi>in fide.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. <hi>In ſanguine. Heb.</hi> 12.4. hee hath appointed them to wreſtle. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. <hi>vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad auroram. Gen.</hi> 32.35. <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſus principatus, adverſus poteſtates, adverſus mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minos. adverſus ſpirituales aſtutias. Eph.</hi> 6.12. hee hath appointed vs to fight. <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.14. <hi>non ſecundum carne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. <hi>ſed bonam militiam militare</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. and in all theſe the life of a Chriſtian is a buſie, ſtirring, agonizing trade of life, a preſſing to the marke a ſtriuing to enter in at the narrowe gate, and a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſupriſing of the kingdome of heauen. So the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine hence to be obſerued is this,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> that Chriſtianitie is not a lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious, or a libertine like ſecuritie but an earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, painful, watchful, Conflicting, Combating life.</p>
            <p>And whoſoeuer wil vndergoe this &amp; be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to take preſſe mony in this warfaring life ſhalbe ſure to haue God ſtil helping ſtrengthning, encouraging, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting, and aſſiſting, ſo that what is faynedly reported
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14045:7"/>of <hi>Pindarus</hi> to be continuallie aſſiſted by <hi>Apollo, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus</hi> by <hi>Pithia, Numa</hi> by <hi>Aegeria, Socrates,</hi> by his <hi>Genius, Phiddias</hi> by his <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and <hi>Philemon</hi> by the <hi>Muſes,</hi> may more truelie be ſaid of the Lord our God, who doeth continuallie aſſiſt his ſeruants to the laſt of their life to ouercome.</p>
            <p>Manie things are ſaid to ouercome, the word of God to ouercome man, that word made man to ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e for man, man himſelfe by repentance and praier to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome God, by faith, hope, &amp; charitie, to ouercome al ſpiritual aduerſaties. The word of God powerful to ouercome ſtrong holdes: and to caſt downe and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw euerie high thing, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. witnes <hi>Niniueh</hi> imperious, inſolent, intollerable <hi>Niniueh, Niniueh,</hi> the imperial co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mander of the Eaſterne parts, prowde of her wals and bulwarks, <hi>Niniveh</hi> the mother Cittie of <hi>Aſsiria,</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the Countrie, the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> head of the picture, the glorie of the earth, the ſeate of the Empire, the Ladie of the Eaſt, and the Queene of the Nations, ſo ſtrong, ſo potent, ouercome with this word, yet fortie daies and <hi>Niniveh</hi> ſhalbe deſtroied. The meſſage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of their ouerthrow, ouerthrew the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuage ſaith <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> the prophecie fel, the Cittie fel not becauſe her fal was prophecied, <hi>Vincit verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The word made man, ouercame for man. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. I haue ouercome the world, witneſſe, that bloodie conflict, when Mount <hi>Calvary</hi> was the field, the <hi>Croſſe</hi> the <hi>bloody banner,</hi> his bleſſed <hi>body</hi> the weapon of his <hi>warfare,</hi> his <hi>anguiſhes</hi> his <hi>armies, My God why haſte thou forſaken me,</hi> the <hi>Trumpet,</hi> his <hi>death,</hi> the <hi>life,</hi> his <hi>miſerie,</hi> the <hi>victorie,</hi> his <hi>crucifying,</hi> the <hi>conqueſt,</hi> his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14045:8"/>
               <hi>Tortours</hi> the <hi>Triumph, Vincit Christus.</hi> Repentance o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercommeth. Affliction is ſaid to ouercome man, and Repentance is ſomewaie ſaid to ouercome God, for as Affliction cauſeth man to turne to God; ſo repetance cauſeth God to turne to man. <hi>Apoſtrophe</hi> in man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God breeds <hi>Apoſtrophe</hi> in God, from man, <hi>Epistro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe</hi> in man to God begets <hi>Epiſtrophe</hi> in God to man. Repentance in man begets Repentance in God, <hi>non per naturam ſed per effectum,</hi> though the heauens bee readie to plague vs, the ſun &amp; moone to raigne downe blood vpon vs, the fire hote burning coles, the aire I hunderbolts, the earth readie to ſwallow vs, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to drowne vs, hel to deuour vs: nay, al the hoſts of the God of hoſts, to ouercome vs, yet by faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance wee ouercome them all. <hi>Vincit Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> Praier doth ouercome. For it is not onlie <hi>Angelis ſolatium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Daemonibus flagellum, animae praeſidiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſpeaketh. But it is more, it is <hi>Eliahs</hi> key, <hi>Moyſes</hi> rod, <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſword and bow, <hi>Davids</hi> ſhield and ſpeare, the moſt powerful of al the weapons of a Chriſtian. I wil fetch but one drop from the Ocean, to proue this. When <hi>Egypt</hi> was ſmitten, and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> plagued, and their waters, and riuers, and ſtreames, and ponds, and pooles, and veſſels of ſtone, were ſilled with blood, and frogs, and lice, and botches, and ſoares, and haile, and thunder, and lightning, and graſhoppers, &amp; morreine, and darknes, were ſent vpon the Countrie, By <hi>Moyſes</hi> praiet they were remoued, diſperſed, ſcattered demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, vtterlie diſſipated as the duſt before the winde. <hi>Vincit Oratio, Oratio paenetrat coelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> So might I ſpeak of faith, hope, and charitie, which be moſt forcible, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14045:8"/>effectual, powerful, energeticallie potent, I had almoſt ſaid omnipotent in the trials, trauils, battels, warfare, combates, conflicts, conqueſts, victories, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, trophes of the Saints.</p>
            <p>To end this point God hath made man a Chriſtian, and dubd euerie Chriſtian a knight,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.</note> prouided him the armor of God, nay God for his armor, giuen ſpirite to his ſword, for it is the ſword of the ſpirit, giuen ſafety to his helmet, for it is the helmet of ſaluation, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe for his breſtplate, for it is the breſt plate of righteouſneſſe, faith for his ſhield, for it is the ſhield of faith, veritie for his girdle, for it is the girdle of veritie, giuen him the Goſpel of Peace for his feet, for his feet bee ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace. This is now that Complete knight, Hauing on his feet ſpurs guilt with his blood, who tooke awaie the guilt of the law, on his head, a helmet ſaluation, on his hart, a breſt plate righteouſneſſe, on his loines, a girdle veritie, in his hand, a ſword the ſpirit, on his whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die a robe, the ſeameleſſe garment the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and vpon this garment putting on an armour, <hi>Armaturam Dei.</hi> naie more, <hi>Armaturam Deum,</hi> the whole armour of God, naie whole God for his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. Euerie man is this Chriſtian, euerie true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian muſt thus arme, watch, ſtand, run, wreſtle, reſiſt, ſtriue, fight and ouercome.</p>
            <p>The vſe of the doctrine is to encite al the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Lord to be Martialiſts to be ſouldiers in this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world. Our life is <hi>militia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> we haue an oath <hi>ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> militiae,</hi> we haue an armour <hi>Armaturam militiae</hi> we haue a place <hi>locum militiae,</hi> we haue a combat <hi>luct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14045:9"/>militiae,</hi> we haue a reward <hi>coronam militiae,</hi> our da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers diuerſe, our conflicts mightie, our adverſaries many,<note place="margin">Cic. pro Arch Poet.</note> 
               <hi>Nihil horu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ora vultus mouerunt?</hi> within vs guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſciences oppreſſing vs, before vs trapps for our deſtruction to enſnare vs, behind vs memorie of ſinns paſt to torture vs, ouer our heads, the wrath of God to terrifie vs, vnder our feet the dungeon of damnation, to entrappe vs, the fleſh inſulting, the world triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the deuil tempting, ſinne ſlinging, <hi>Nihil horum ora vultuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mouerunt?</hi> Wel my beloued at the length Ariſe, arme your ſelues fight the Lords battels. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the yonge Prince did more earneſtly deſire to learn, becauſe <hi>Ariſt.</hi> the Prince of Philoſophers taught him, And the ſouldiers did more ſtreniouſly fight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the renowned <hi>Alexander</hi> did lead them Beloued your <hi>Ariſt.</hi> is Alexander, your Alexander is Chriſt, hee doth teach you to fight and doth fight to teach you, In him yee are Conquerours, by him yee are more then Conquerours. Neuer did any Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſo victoriouſly, if you fight as ye haue him for an example. The <hi>Philiſtin</hi> with his ſpeare, the <hi>Iſraelite</hi> with his ſlinge, the <hi>Indian</hi> with his darre, the <hi>Perſian</hi> with his bow, the <hi>Schithian</hi> with his launce, the <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madon</hi> with his ſtrength was neuer able to be ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull in conflict as thou mayſt bee, And as the conflict is victorious ſo the victorie is as glorious, neuer had <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuch a victorie ouer the <hi>Caananits, Ioſhua</hi> ouer 31. kingly Captaines, <hi>Iſrael</hi> ouer the <hi>Philiſtins, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ouer the <hi>Amalekits, Alex.</hi> ouer the <hi>Barbaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles</hi> ouer the <hi>Perſians, Aemilius</hi> ouer the <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians, Marcellus</hi> ouer the <hi>Sithia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> or <hi>Scipio</hi> ouer the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14045:9"/>
               <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> as thou maiſt thy ſelfe obtaine by thy Chriſt. O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who would not in a ſpiritual ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier ſo to triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph, ſo to Celebrat his Trophies. But yet if any wil deſire this, let him remember the tenour of his knights ſeruice is the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and as the <hi>Romans</hi> coulde not come to the temple of <hi>honour,</hi> but by the Temple of <hi>vertue,</hi> ſo hee by noe meanes can come to the <hi>Crowne</hi> but by the <hi>Croſſe.</hi> Hee muſt come to fight before hee fight to ouercome. He muſt ouercome the world, the deuil, the fleſh, in the world, he muſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come himſelfe a little world, in himſelfe he muſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his tongue a world of wickednes, himſelfe a little world in the great worlde, his tongue a great worlde in that little world, a world of wickedneſſe. <hi>Iames</hi> 3.6. If he can ouercome the world and himſelfe, he ſhalbe able to ouercome tribulation, anguiſh, perſecution, fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine, nakedneſſe, perill, ſword, life, death, angels, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, powers, things preſent, or things to come, height or depth, or any other creature eſpecially if he be able to ouercome &amp; to hold faſt til C. come. For the promiſe is made to him that ouercometh and keepeth my workes to the end, and ſo J end this point &amp; come to ſhew that wee muſt ouercome to the end.</p>
            <p>Not the hearers but the the doers of the lawe are iuſtified. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13.<note place="margin">2. Obſ. 1. part.</note> Not the doers for a time but the continuers, beyond time, the faithful vnto the death, <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.10 Many herd C who vnderſtood him not, ſo the vulgar <hi>Iewes,</hi> many vnderſtood him who beleued him not ſo the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſes,</hi> many beleeued him who profeſt him not ſo the <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> many profeſſed him for a time, but after fel away ſo the <hi>Apoſtats.</hi> This an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14045:10"/>al <hi>Iewes-Scribes Phariſais Hypocrits</hi> &amp; <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, hee that keepeth my workes to the end.</hi> Not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but keepeth, not words, but workes not for a time but to the ende, <hi>hee that keepeth my woorkes to the end</hi> to him and to none but to him.</p>
            <p>It was a brutiſh ſpeach of <hi>Brutus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liuy</note> 
               <hi>Te colui virtus vt rem aſt tu nomen inane es,</hi> that <hi>Pietie, Honestie, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> bee but names, for Chriſt here makes a ſufficient explication of his will in theſe words, <hi>Hee that keepeth my workes vnto the ende,</hi> giueth the name, and nature, the words, and workes, affections, and actions, al that is to be performed. The in vndation of hipocriſie hath almoſt drowned the world how many good woordes, in the world, how ſewe good workes, how many bee like <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yet noe <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> like <hi>Profeſſours</hi> yet no <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of whom the obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Guicciardine</hi> maie be true <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> and his father Pope <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the 6 had a prouerb faſtened on them by the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talians</hi> of that time,<note place="margin">Guicc. lib. 5.</note> that the one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer thought as he ſpake, and the other neuer ſpake as hee thought. Many are like to <hi>Panarches aenigma,</hi> to the Poets <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maphrodites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Athaen. Dipno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoph.</note> to the Grammarians <hi>Participles,</hi> to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles</hi> which are fiſh and noe fiſh, foule and noe foule: many are outward not inward Chriſtians, <hi>extra mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo, non intramittendo,</hi> by profeſſion not by practiſe by ſight not by faith.</p>
            <p>God requireth the <hi>externe</hi> and <hi>interne,</hi> ſoule &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, hart and face, words and works, hee requireth that his ſeruaunt ſhoulde not onlie keepe the waies of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and the couenants of the Lorde, 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 11.11. and the commandements of the Lorde,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14045:10"/>
               <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.5. and the Sabaoths of the Lord, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.2. and the ceremonies of the Lord, 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 2.3. and the iudgements of the Lord, <hi>Eſec.</hi> 18.19. the ſtatuts of the Lord, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.5. and the words of the Lord, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.7. but here <hi>the works of the Lord</hi> which <hi>Hugo</hi> expreſſeth to be <hi>mandata</hi> the precepts, or as he expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the practiſe of the precepts of the Lord.</p>
            <p>In which words, <hi>to keepe my works,</hi> hee ioineth faith &amp; works togither, to keepe <hi>credendo</hi> my works. <hi>faciendo,</hi> to keep by beleeuing, to expreſſe by practiſing. For the Goſpel is not a doctrine of libertie, Epicuriſme or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualitie, but a Goſpel of exact action &amp; perfection, not a goſpel of beleeuing only, but of liuing, not of <hi>Theorie</hi> onlie, but of <hi>practique,</hi> conſiſting not in hearing, but doing, not in affecting, but an effecting faith So that hence J obſerue this doctrine that true Chriſtianitie muſt be manifeſted in a liuely, effectual,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> powerful pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſe, otherwiſe our faith is no faith, our faith muſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the only knowing faith of the <hi>Deuils,</hi> for that is <hi>Hiſtorical,</hi> from the bragging faith of the <hi>Iewes</hi> for that is <hi>Phariſaicall,</hi> from the bare faith of <hi>Hypocrits,</hi> for that is <hi>vneffectuall,</hi> from the fained faith of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates,</hi> for that is but <hi>Temporall,</hi> from the falſe faith of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for that is <hi>phantaſticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A doctrine verie needful in theſe our times where in works are changed into words, walking into talking hands into tongues, harts into eares, which hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Romaine faction</hi> to traduce vs for a <hi>ſolyfidian profeſsion,</hi> as if we did pluck vp good works as weeds, and caſt them out of dores: which how much contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to our profeſſion it is, anie indicious &amp; ingenuous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14045:11"/>maie vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. So we that hold this againſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that a true, effectual, liuely faith doth onlie iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, ſo that we remoue not works from faith, but works from iuſtifying. We grant works to bee <hi>vta regni non cauſa regnandi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Aquin. Hil. Origen.</note> as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh, and to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>neceſsitate praeſentiae, non neceſsitate efficientiae,</hi> for as <hi>Hilary</hi> in his Comment vpon <hi>Math.</hi> teacheth, <hi>Fides ſola iuſtificat,</hi> and S. <hi>Auſten</hi> on the 4. of the <hi>Rom. fides ſola mundat,</hi> and as <hi>Origen</hi> on the ſame Chapter, <hi>fides ſola ſufficit.</hi> But then they replie out of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> yee ſee ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that of works a man is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and not of faith onlie. Yea but ſaith S. <hi>Paule,</hi> we conclude that a man is iuſtified by faith, without the worke of the Lawe. To reconcile both which places I ſaie, that as we are iuſtified by faith without the works of the Law, ſo by the works of the Law muſt our faith be iuſtified. So that there is one righteouſneſſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, another righteouſneſſe excerciſed, there is a iuſtice of iuſtification, and a iuſtice of teſtification, the one acquiteth before God, the other approueth before men. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of the former of theſe two, <hi>Iames</hi> of the later. The one eſtabliſhing a real, Chriſtian, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith,<note place="margin">Aquin.</note> the other confuting a falſe, fained, dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh faith, <hi>Aquinas</hi> in this one diſtinction ending this <hi>Chriſtus iuſtificat effectiue, fides iuſtificat apprehenſiue, opera iuſtificant declaratiue,</hi> our works by faith, &amp; faith by Chriſt doth iuſtifie vs. Our workes maie claime a part in our faith, but not in our iuſtifying, for in that great act of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celing the handwriting, acquiting the conſcience, pacifying Gods anger, and preſenting vs blameleſſe before Gods holy eies, <hi>faith</hi> is wholie and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14045:11"/>ſolely imploied, and our works not claiming anie part therein.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not this to ſtoppe the bleſſed fountaine of good works, I know that he that hath proclaimed of <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> whereſoeuer this Goſpel ſhalbe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, mention ſhalbe made of this woman, he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo promiſed that hee that ſhall giue to one of the leſt the verie leaſt gifte, a Cup of cold water in his name ſhal not want their reward. And therefore if any haue beene to buſie in this kinde, I ſay to ſuch, why cauſe ye the people to ſtaie from their workes, get ye to your burdens, laie vpon the people the number of workes which they did in the beginning diminiſh nothing thereof, for they be idle, let them worke and worke, &amp; continue in working, that when Chriſt commeth to iudgment he maie finde them working, and ſaie, <hi>good ſervants and faithful yee haue beene faithfull in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, I will make you rulers over much, enter into your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the vſe of this doctrine mooue you al to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate your external, and internal,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> inward &amp; outwarde actions, vnto God, that ye maie ſhew forth the vertue of him that hath called you, if yee haue onlie <hi>outwarde ſanctity</hi> ye deceiue others, if <hi>only inward,</hi> you deceiue your ſelues: if neither <hi>inward,</hi> nor <hi>outward,</hi> ye deceiue God. But be ye not deceiued, God is not mocked. S. <hi>Peter</hi> proueth, that <hi>if temperance, patience, godlineſſe, brotherly kindneſſe and loue be in you, you ſhall neither be idle nor vnfruitfull in the knowledge of Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Amor Dei</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorie, otioſus non est, operatur magna, ſi eſt, ſi operari renuerit amor non eſt,</hi> where the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14045:12"/>loue of God is, it is not idle, and where it is idle it is not. Be earneſt, zealous, religious, and be ye ſo religiouſlie zealous, that you maie continue to the end, for <hi>Nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni palma datur priuſquam curſus conficiatur,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God required not a working only, but a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing perſeuering, keeping to the end. For the end of that ſhal be rewarded. O beloued ſhal not wee continue, <hi>Tantum boni in bono quantum mali in malo?</hi> ſhall the drunkard continue ſo long as his longues laſt, the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer ſo long as his loines laſt, the glutton while his ſkin, the prowd man while his purſe, the wicked man while his life, and ſhal not we continue? To the ende that you maie continue to the ende, Remember that God in his Arithmetique requireth Multiplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not Subſtraction, in his iournies <hi>progreds</hi> not <hi>regredi,</hi> in his Philoſophie <hi>motum velociorem in fine quam in princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pio.</hi> Miſtake me not, I ſaie he requireth <hi>motum velocio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> not <hi>violentiorem,</hi> for I know violent motions be vnnatural, and yet there haue beene latelie ſo many vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent motions in our Church, that had not the diuine gubernation of our <hi>primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> movens</hi> reſtrained the heat of inferiour Spheres, our Church had beene on fire &amp; the <hi>Clerolaicall preſbiterie</hi> had brought among vs a Cyclopical anarchy. But I need not to bring theſe in publicke. <hi>Theophilact</hi> vpon <hi>Luke,</hi> obſerueth that Lady <hi>Philautia, Lady ſelfe loue</hi> was maried to the <hi>Phariſie</hi> in the Goſpel.<note place="margin">Theoph. in Luk.</note> The <hi>Phariſie</hi> I am ſure is dead, ſhee was then left a widdow. The <hi>Anabaptists, Brownists, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roniſts,</hi> and <hi>Humoriſts,</hi> are in competition yet for her, The <hi>Preſbiterie</hi> is corriual with them, they much tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture themſelues in the ſuit, we are not much troubled
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14045:12"/>with them, and I hope, we ſhal be leſſe. I come not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to trample them, if there be anie thing good in them I honor it, the exorbitancie I pitty, I would they would reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that as <hi>knowledge without zeale is not religion, ſo zeale without knowledge is not diſcretion.</hi> They would not then be ſo violent and virulent.</p>
            <p>Our motions beloued, they muſt not bee violent as theſe but natural, it muſt bee a <hi>perpetual motion</hi> to the end, we maie ſtretch out our ſelues but not out ſtretch our ſelues, runne but not ouerrunne, wee muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in a ciuil, ſober, ſanctified courſe, runing our race, fighting our fight, til wee haue finiſhed our courſe, &amp; we ſhalbe ſure to finde help in running, comfort in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuing, ioye in obtaineing, a reward in triumphing, though al the world bee againſt vs, yet wee ſhalbee as <hi>Mount Syon</hi> that ſhal not bee remoued, as <hi>Socrates</hi> whoe neuer changed countenance, or as the <hi>Cypreſſe tree</hi> which neuer changeth colour. Troubles maie aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault the godly, but neuer inſult ouer them, they ſhall haue a <hi>refection</hi> in their <hi>affliction,</hi> and <hi>Conſolation</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>deſolation poſt praelium praemium,</hi> and ſo J come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>praelium</hi> to <hi>praemium,</hi> my ſecond part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will giue him power ouer nations,</hi> were there not greater reward for delightinging in the Lord then the delight of that delight, the ioie of that ioie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pars.</note> the pleſure of that pleaſure it were ſufficient <hi>dilectionis nulla ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior expetenda eſt remuneratio quam ipſa dilectio</hi> ſaieth <hi>leo.</hi> But behold the bountifulneſſe, mercy, liberalitie, munificens of our good god, hee inciteth, and allur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and heareth, and promiſeth wages, yea promiſeth to reward his owne merits in vs, by his owne mercy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14045:13"/>on vs. So true is hee in his word, ſo faithfull in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, man cannot obiect againſt God,<note place="margin">Ouid. Met.</note> as the Poet doth againſt man <hi>Mobilis Aeſonide verna<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> incertior aura curtua policiti pondere verba care<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> He deſerueth not to bee called <hi>Doſo</hi> as <hi>Antigonus</hi> was who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed much and performed little, hee wil not <hi>equiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> with man, as hee did that promiſed <hi>centum oues</hi> &amp; brought but <hi>centum oua, Auſtine</hi> witneſſeth <hi>Deum feciſſe Chirographum promiſſorum ſuorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>non deben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſed promittendo.</hi> Hee oweth vs nothing, becauſe he neuer receaued anie thing, and yet he maketh his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe his debt, his deed, his word, his worke, &amp; his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy a merit, yet not our merit, for <hi>St</hi>-<hi>Paul</hi> anticipateth the doctrine of merits in the 2. Eph. 8. wee are ſaued not of our ſelues, not of our workes, leaſt any man ſhold boaſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but it is the gift of god wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>Bernard</hi> concludeth <hi>demeritis ſufficit ſcire quod non ſufficiant merita.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> So that againe I ſaie he promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to reward his owne merits by his owne mercies, he promiſeth this and hee performeth this, his worde, his deed, his promiſes, his reward, be not as the worlds bee. In the world ſome promiſe what they cannot doe as <hi>Sathan</hi> to Chriſt <hi>Math.</hi> 4.9. ſome what they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe but meane not, as the ſonns of <hi>Iacob</hi> to the ſonnes of <hi>Sichem Gen</hi> 34 16. Some what they meene for a time but afterwards deny it, as <hi>Laban</hi> did to <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 29.23. Some what they promiſe willinglie, but giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willinglie, as <hi>Herod Io. Baptiſts</hi> head. <hi>Mark.</hi> 6.16. So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e what they giue willingly but afterwards repent, as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> his graunt to the <hi>Gibeonits. Ioſ.</hi> 9.23. But Gods promiſes bee performances, and therfore bee to bee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14045:13"/>beleeued, <hi>In ſpe, extra ſpem-ſupra ſpem, contra ſpem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this God hath done with man as the rulers of ſtates, and makers of ſtatutes, who haue ſought not only to puniſh the bad, and to prouide ſome ſharpe &amp; fearful tortors for them, but haue euer a regard to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corage and reward the vertuous office of the God. So did <hi>Zoroaster</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the <hi>Perſians, Triſmegiſtus</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the <hi>Aegyptians, Charondas</hi> among the <hi>Carthaginians, Minos</hi> among the <hi>Cretians,</hi> &amp; <hi>Solon</hi> among the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> that as in <hi>Hercul. Biuiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> they were 2 waies, the on <hi>via virtutis Non est ad aſtra mollis è terris via,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>via voluptatis, facilis deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſus Auerni.</hi> So there ſhould bee alſo diuerſe reſpects had for the followers of theſe two diuerſe waies, as <hi>Antiſhenes</hi> the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher in <hi>Laertius</hi> and <hi>Achilles,</hi> that valiant martia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt in <hi>Homer</hi> doe teſtifie. So God the life giuer of all, theſe law-giuers, hath prouided the one and the other for the wicked whoe wil bee warned by noe warning, feared by noe threatning, affrighted by noe terrifying admoniſhed by noe exhorting, he hath prouide fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and horrid and eternal <hi>paines,</hi> tumultuous <hi>horrour,</hi> firie <hi>Chaines,</hi> flamming <hi>whipps,</hi> ſchorching <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> tormenting <hi>Deuills,</hi> vpon whom houling, roaring, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, blaſpheming, and eternal death gnawing on them, ſhalbe powred out, the ful flood of Gods wrath and the dreggs of the vnſauorie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſition of the cup of Gods diſpleſure.</p>
            <p>But for his ſeruants (as in al other things he is a god of great mercy, magnificence, liberalitie, and princely munificence ſoe) in this aboue all the reſt, hee is moſt munificent in rewarding his Saints, and ſeruants, with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14045:14"/>many, and moſt infinite bleſſings, as hee often promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth &amp; here expreſſeth <hi>I will giue,</hi> out of which words J obſerue this doctrine,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> that God is able and willing to reward his Saints that which he promiſeth. The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture giueth proofe to this doctrine. God hath made promiſes before the begining of the world. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. firme and ſtable promiſes. 2, <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8. moſt greate and pretious promiſes. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. hauing a time of promiſe <hi>Act.</hi> 7 17. giuen a word of promiſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7. proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Goſpel of promiſe 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. purchaſed inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of promiſe <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12. adopted ſonns of promiſe <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28. drawen couenants of promiſe <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the ſpirit as the ſcriuener of theſe couenants of promiſe <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14 and added yea and Anen as a ſeal to theſe couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of promiſe. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. So that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may now be ſure that al bands, bills, obligations, leaſes, Indentures, alienations, contracts, Couenants made neuer ſo curiouſly by the <hi>Meander</hi> of Lawyers wit ſhalbe annihilated before the leaſt of the promiſes ſhal faile, nay heauen and earth ſhall faile before the leaſt <hi>Iota</hi> of his promiſe.</p>
            <p>The comfort of this made <hi>St</hi>-<hi>Bernard</hi> to be almoſt in a heuenly extaſie, when hee conſidered, <hi>Charitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adoptionis, Veritatem Promiſſionis Poteſtatem red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionis,</hi> Gods loue in adopting his truth in promiſing and his power in performeing, and ſurely it cannot chooſe but ſtirre and incite euerie true Chriſtian to a moſt feruent and earneſt embraceing, of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p>Let the vſe therfore of this Doctrine bee this, <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> that wee remoue al miſdoubting &amp; vnbeleeuing thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14045:14"/>from vs that at no time there bee found an euil minde in vs, not crediting the promiſe of God. Let vs aſſure our ſelues that if we can <hi>credere &amp; vivere</hi> beleeue and liue after our beliefe, we ſhal ſurely receiue the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this promiſe in due time. The bargaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and vs, is <hi>Crede quod habes &amp; habes,</hi> like to <hi>Ithiell</hi> and <hi>Vcall. Ithiell</hi> ſignifieth God with vs, <hi>Vcall</hi> is to preuaile, ſo that <hi>Ithiell</hi> and <hi>Vcall</hi> muſt go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, if we preuaile God is with vs. It is double, a mutual, reciprocal, interchangeable dutie, a twofolde <hi>Indenture</hi> on our behalfe, as wel, as on Gods. If we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome he hath promiſed, and hauing promiſed, hee wil performe, he wil giue to him that ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer nations, &amp; ſo I come in few words to the laſt &amp; beſt words of my Text.<note place="margin">Vlt Cir</note> 
               <hi>I wil giue him power ouer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a <hi>power</hi> giuen, &amp; a power <hi>vſurped,</hi> a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er giuen to man ouer Gods creatures, giuen to the K. ouer men. A power vſurped by the Deuil ouer Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, by the Tyrants ouer kingdomes, by the Pope o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Kings; for the Pope hearing that the Diuell hath power, he thinketh that he alſo may haue a power, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the Deuils vicegerent in cauſes Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Temporal: but in this the Pope is deceiued for the Deuils <hi>patent</hi> is more <hi>potent,</hi> his <hi>power</hi> ſtronger &amp; and longer then the Popes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his 1. booke <hi>de ſumo Pontifice</hi> the 22. Chapter, and ſince <hi>Baronius</hi> in his letter to <hi>Paule</hi> the <hi>Venetian</hi> proue out of ſcripture, that the Pope hath ſpecial power, and is the head of the Church, out of the <hi>Acts,</hi> 10.13. Kil &amp; eate. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proueth it out
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14045:15"/>of the word <hi>Eate, Baronius</hi> out of the word <hi>kill,</hi> a kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling argument, I ſhould thinke <hi>Bellarmine</hi> might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proue him out of the word <hi>eate,</hi> to be the <hi>mouth</hi> then the <hi>head</hi> &amp; <hi>Baronius</hi> might <hi>prone</hi> out of the word <hi>kill,</hi> that he is not the <hi>head,</hi> but the <hi>headſman</hi> of the Church. For out of the word <hi>eate,</hi> we maie conclude him to bee the mouth &amp; I maie ſaie as <hi>Cato</hi> ſpake to <hi>Lentulus, Dicam cos falli qui te negant habere os,</hi> I ſaie they are much deceiued, who denie him to haue a mouth and a fowle one to. Euen ſuch a mouth as vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth blaſphemies. Whoſe lips haue the poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Aſpes.</hi> Whoſe tongue is ſharpned like a Serpents. Whoſe teeth be like to Lions teeth. And whoſe throat is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſepulchre. Yea a deuouring <hi>Sheol,</hi> hel it ſelfe. Thus he is the <hi>mouth.</hi> Now that he is not ſo much the <hi>head</hi> as the <hi>headſman</hi> of the Church, may be proued by thoſe manie <hi>ſtratagems, engines, tortures, burnings, broylings rackings, dilaniating, murthering,</hi> &amp; <hi>maſsacring,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Pope</hi> hath made the <hi>Church</hi> the ſhame &amp; ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the worlde, as maie be ſeene by the manifolde floods of warm, reaking, gore blood, that he hath ſhed and by the ſoules of the Martyrs crying vnder the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>How long Lord Ieſus. Bellarmine and Baronius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in this are like to thoſe wicked Iudges,</hi> founde in a diuerſe tale, the one out of <hi>kill,</hi> the other out of <hi>eate,</hi> making him their head, and therfore they well deſeruing by him to bee rewarded, the one by beeing his <hi>butcher,</hi> the other his <hi>cooke,</hi> I could proceed further in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing of this child of the deuil and father of darknes, whoſe religion is rebellion, whoſe planters are ſuppla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whoſe profeſſors be Traitors, whoſe oracles bee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14045:15"/>lyes, whoſe miracles bee ſtrawes. But J come to my Text. Jn that <hi>poteſtes data</hi> wee muſt conſider another 2 fold power, power in <hi>hoc ſeculo,</hi> power in <hi>futuro.</hi> That the Saints of God ſhal enioie power ouer nations, <hi>In hoc ſeculo</hi> as the <hi>Gloſſe</hi> interpreteth <hi>in finali Iudicio</hi> as <hi>Lyra</hi> readeth, <hi>In vtro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. Lyra. Auſtin. Hugo. Hierom.</note> In this life to come <hi>ſuper motus Carnales</hi> ſaith <hi>Hugo,</hi> &amp; in this life to come <hi>ſuper thronos iudica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes tribus Iſraell</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierome.</hi> So that here, and hence, in this life and that to come in earth and in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The <hi>Saints</hi> ſhalbe ſure to receiue power ouer Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the <hi>Doctrine</hi> is this that the Saints of God ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in this in God &amp; in the life to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e with God more true glory, and honour, and power, then euer any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch had vpon the earth. I need not to proue this the verie text promiſeth to giue power ouer nations. This power Chriſt calleth a kingdome, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. <hi>Math.</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it an heauenlie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Luke</hi> a bleſſed king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Peter</hi> an eternal kingdome, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. &amp; becauſe you ſhal not thinke it a kingdome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Crowne, C. hath promiſed a Crowne, yea an immarceſſible Crowne 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. and to the ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble price, hee hath added glorie a Crowne of glorie, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28.5. and to this glorie hee hath added Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, a Crowne of righteouſnes. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8 and to this righteouſneſſe hee hath added life, a Crowne of life. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.10.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The vſe of this doctrine is to enflame the ſoules of the godlie, and to ſtir them vp to the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this kingdome. All the world cannot afforde more riches, honour, pleaſure glorie, power, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of ioieful comfort, then this kingdome. O then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14045:16"/>ſtriue, reſiſt, wreſtle, run the race, fight the finiſh the courſe that you maie ouercome.</p>
            <p>My moſt gratious ſoueraigne let it not be offenſiue that I haue beeene ſo bould in a time of ſuch gratious and glorious <hi>peace</hi> to moue this aſſembly to fight eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſeeing the Goſpel, <hi>is a Goſpel of peace, &amp; we that preach that Goſpel are bound to the peace by S. Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing I haue begun to ſpeake, <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.3.</note> O let not my Lord the king be now angry, God hath choſen and apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and anointed your Maieſtie, to fight his battels, hee hath giuen you the head of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the hart of <hi>Dauid</hi> hand of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> to make you able to ouercome. Hee hath already giuen you power ouer nations, in the va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing of <hi>Hereſie, Poperie, Idolatrie.</hi> He hath enabled your highneſſe in this high woorke, to <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in one kingdome, to <hi>confirme</hi> it in a nother, to <hi>found</hi> it in on, to <hi>finde</hi> it in a nother, to <hi>plant</hi> it in the oue, to water it in the other, and at the length to ioine both in on, ſo that <hi>male diut ſum,</hi> is become <hi>bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> O let theſe kingdomes neuer knowe that <hi>falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie a bene coniunctis ad male diuiſa,</hi> Thoſe that God hath ioined to gether let no man put a ſander.</p>
            <p>If euer the Lord verified that prophecy of <hi>Eſekiell, Faciam eos ingentem vnam,</hi> hee hath now ſurely, they are one, and noe more two peoples neither deuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, ſo that your Maieſtie may ſaie with <hi>Caeſar veni vidi vici</hi> but J hope your Maieſtie will rather ſpeak with (a more Chriſtian <hi>Caeſar</hi> then he was) <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus Quintus</hi> whoſe woords were <hi>vidi, veni, at Deus vicit,</hi> by him you liue, moue, breath, haue being to be a King and Conquerour. For if euer God ouercame
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14045:16"/>for any, or ever any ouer came by God, your Maieſtie maie glorie in it, as much as euer any that breathed &amp; J maie ſaie that God ouercame more gloriouſly for you by a weake, ſmall vnimaginarie, Charactericall armie then euer he did, by the <hi>ſun</hi> againſt the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits</hi> by the <hi>fier</hi> againſt the <hi>Sodomits,</hi> by the <hi>ſtarrs</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Cananits,</hi> by the <hi>water</hi> againſt the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> or by the <hi>earth</hi> againſt the <hi>Murmerers,</hi> hee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came more powerfully, more miraculouſly for your highneſſe in an <hi>army of letters,</hi> by a Schedule, ſchrole, paper gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of their owne making, then euer be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came for anie ſince the firſt daie of the world. As hee hath ouercome for your Maieſtie, ſo hath hee apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Maieſtie to ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e for him, to ouercome and Conquer all the monſters you find in this king dome, the <hi>Bethauen</hi> of <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> the <hi>Gilgall</hi> of <hi>Hereſie</hi> the houſes of <hi>bribery,</hi> the Churches of <hi>Symony,</hi> the ſeats of <hi>iniuſtice,</hi> and offices of <hi>oppreſsion,</hi> the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>ſacriledge</hi> the profeſſions of <hi>Athesſme, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaveliſme, Anabaptiſme, Barrowiſme, Paganiſme, Pa piſme, And this ſhall be the victory, whereby yee ſhal o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome even your faith,</hi> your Maieſtie is the <hi>defender</hi> of the faith, O be an <hi>overcomer</hi> in this faith, that ſo this land maie obey you, your ſubiectes maie ſerue you your ſeruants may praie for you, the whole world may honor you, the Lord may reward you. And there may neuer be wanting one of your roial ſeede to ſit in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and happines vpon the throne of theſe kingdomes vntil Chriſt Ieſus come to iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Let al true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſubiects ſaie <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>Honourable Lordes,</hi> yee oracles of our wiſdome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14045:17"/>and Chariots of our Jſrael, ſeeing I haue beene bold to ſpeake vnto my Lord the King, let mee finde fauour in your ſight to ſhew you, how you maie finde fauour in Gods ſight Heauen is the hauen whether ye deſire to come, otherwiſe though now your ſtate be <hi>honorable</hi> it wil be moſt <hi>miſerable.</hi> To heauen if ye deſire to <hi>come</hi> here ye muſt <hi>overcome,</hi> yea you your ſelues my thrice Hon: Lords muſt your ſelues endeuour to ouercome, though worthilie you be imploied in the greateſt ſtate of the kingdome, O forget not the ſtate of the greateſt kingdome, though yee be <hi>Domint Terrae,</hi> yet yee are but <hi>terra Demint,</hi> &amp; though yee were the Lords of the whoſe world, yet the whole world cannot ouercome for you. Jt is only your faith, this is the aime, the ſcope the marke, the armour, the complement, the weapon of your warfare, the victorie of your combat eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your faith. Not your wit, wiſdome, honour, followers, not armies, not navies be able to ouercome for you. Not wit, it is vertues wanton, iudgments ouerthrow. Not wiſcom it is the peoples talke, the ſtatiſts opinion. Not eloquence, it is deceipts Councellour, Hipocriſies ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancer. Not honour, it is ennies obiect, cares ſubiect. Not friends, they are but profits guard, affections we thercockes. Not armies, they are wraths executioners deaths purſeuants. Not navies, they are the Oceans wracke, and the windes run awaies. Not al the world and the power thereof, for the victorie of that power, is but the ſwords whetſtone, and cruelties want. O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remember the weapons of your warfare are not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but ſpiritual, &amp; therefore take vnto you the whole Armour of God, that yee maie bee able to reſiſt in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14045:17"/>euil daie, &amp; hauing finiſhed all things <hi>ſtand faſt.</hi> Yee haue latelie celebrated the feſtiuitie of <hi>S. Georges</hi> knights, with manie laudable, honourable, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ceremonies. Long maie yee ſo celebrate it to the glorie of your God, ioie of your King, honor of your nation, and eternal perpetuitie of loue among your ſelues. Might I preſume I could ſhew your Honors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother order of knighthood, not an new order, for I am ſure it was the firſt that euer was in Chriſtendome and in the ſcriptures heraldrie you maie finde it em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſoned by the proper armes, robes, motto, Schutchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that belong to this order,<note place="margin">The order of S. Vincent.</note> it is the order of the Saint in my Text, <hi>Vincenti,</hi> the order of Saint <hi>Vincent.</hi> But it is ſuch an order, that whoſoeuer be knights of this order, muſt firſt be knights of the bath, they muſtwaſh and bathe themſelues as <hi>David</hi> did, and then they ſhal be dubd and double knighted, and then <hi>God</hi> who is the <hi>ſoveraigne</hi> of the order, and <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the Prince of Peace, the <hi>Preſident</hi> of the order, and the <hi>holy ſpirit,</hi> the Biſhop of our ſoules, and <hi>Prelate</hi> of the order, and the <hi>Angels</hi> the guardians, and <hi>heavenly heralds</hi> of that order ſhal bring forth the <hi>vnder robe purity,</hi> the <hi>vpper robe righteouſnes,</hi> the <hi>Helmet ſalvation,</hi> the <hi>ſword</hi> the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> the <hi>Eſchouchion</hi> a <hi>white croſſe,</hi> in a <hi>bloody fielde,</hi> vnder the <hi>Croſse</hi> a <hi>Serpent</hi> latent and a <hi>Lyon</hi> coucha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>Death and hell,</hi> ouer <hi>the Croſſe</hi> a <hi>Crowne triumphant,</hi> a <hi>lawrell ſlorant honour</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> and the <hi>motto Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi dabitur.</hi> And this is the moſt honorable order of knighthood, he that is of this order of <hi>S. Vincent</hi> is not onlie a knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> but a knight of S. <hi>Michaell,</hi> for he hath overcome the deuil, and a knight of <hi>Saint
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14045:18"/>George,</hi> for he hath ouercome the olde <hi>Dragon,</hi> and a knight of the <hi>Temple,</hi> for he is the <hi>Temple of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and a knight of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> for the <hi>holy ſpirit of God dwelleth in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that yee were ſuch knights, ſuch Conquerours? I ſhoulde nowe returne againe vnto <hi>my Lorde the King,</hi> to beſeech his Maieſtie, to eſtabliſh this order, but who am I, that ſhould I preſume ſo much? I feare mee, I haue already preſumed to too much, I wil goe to my heaunely Lord the King, &amp; beſeech him to eſtabliſh it in you all, that you may all ouercome, &amp; be al rewarded, &amp; that what at this time yee haue herd carefully, you maie conceaue rightly, beleeue faithful lie, diſcerne fruitfullie, and practiſe effectually, that at the length you may receaue your reward in the Court of that celeſtial Citye, the gates wherof bee of pearle, the ſtreets of gold, the walls of pretious ſtones, the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple God, the light the lambe, the Cheere ioye, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſinging, the Quire Angells, &amp; the Hymne <hi>Hale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiah. Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14045:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
